good afternoon welcome to the
MARCH 18th 2025 regular meeting
of the san francisco board of
supervisors.
MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Yes, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan chen present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor engardio and
engardio present supervisor
fielder field are present
supervisor mahmud mahmood
present supervisor mandolin
present mandolin present
supervisor melgar melgar
present supervisor sadr sadr
present supervisor sherril
sheryl present supervisor
walton walton present MR.
PRESIDENT all members are
present.
thank you MADAM Clerk the
san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the roman jewish
aloni who are the original
inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula as the
indigenous stewards of this
land and in accordance with
their traditions the
ramakrishna loni have never
ceded lost nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional homeland.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging our ancestors,
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
ramakrishna aloni community and
by affirming their sovereign
rights as first peoples.
Colleagues, will you join me
in saying the pledge of
allegiance to the flag united
states of america in the
republic for which it stands
one nation under GOD
indivisible with liberty and
justice for all.
on behalf of the board I
want to acknowledge the staff
at S.F. Gov tv and today
particularly kaleena mendoza
they record each of our
meetings and make the
transcripts available to the
public online and we appreciate
them.
MADAM Clerk, are there any
communications?
yes.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes your
attendance at this meeting
in the board's legislative
chamber room to 52nd floor and
city hall.
You MAY also watch the
proceedings on S.F. Gov tv's
channel 26 or view the
livestream at ww w dot S.F. Geo
vtv york.
To submit your public comments
send an email to boss at fco v
your or via U.S. Postal service
to the san francisco board of
supervisors.
Number one DR. Carlton be good
place city hall room 244 san
francisco california nine 4102.
to make a reasonable
accommodation request under the
americans with disabilities act
order or request language
assistance please contact the
clerk's office at least two
business days in advance by
calling (415) 554-5184.
And finally, MR. PRESIDENT, our
office is in receipt of an ada
accommodation request to
provide comment as a first
speaker during general public
comment.
So when general public comment
is called we will pull up that
request your first.
That concludes my communication
.
Great.
And thank you MADAM Clerk.
Let's go to approval of the
meeting minutes.
today we're approving the
FEBRUARY 11th, 2025 board
meeting minutes.
all rights.
Colleagues two are there any
changes to the meeting minutes?
I don't see anyone.
Can we have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented move
by sherril seconded by walton.
MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll on the minutes
supervisor sartor sartor I
supervisor sherril sherril.
I supervisor walton walton I.
Supervisor chan chan.
I supervisor chen chen.
I supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio and
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor bamboo
mahmud I supervisor mandolin
mandolin I supervisor melgar
melgar I there are lebanese.
all right then without
objection the minutes will be
approved after public comment
as presented MADAM Clerk let's
go to our regular agenda
unfinished business please call
item number one.
yes.
Item number one is an ordinance
to amend the business and tax
regulations code to authorize a
tax collector to waive taxes,
penalties and or interest under
a program that allows
unregistered taxpayers to
voluntarily voluntarily
disclose and pay back taxes and
to authorize a tax collector to
collect fees through DECEMBER
31st, 2027.
all right, MADAM Clerk,
please call the roll on this
item on item number one
supervisor sartor sardar I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chan I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio and
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmud
mahmood I supervisor amendment
hi hi supervisor melgar melgar
I there are 11 nice all right
without objection this
ordinance is finally passed.
MADAM Clerk can you please
call item number two?
Item number two is an ordinance
to amend the business and tax
regulations code to suspend the
empty homes tax pending a final
decision on a pending lawsuit
to reinstate that tax so at
first applies in the tax year
immediately following the
calendar year of that final
decision and in court and
in accordance with section 2961
of article 29 a the business
and tax regulations code
passage of this ordinance
requires an affirmative vote
two of two thirds of the board
of supervisors.
supervisor fielder thank you
PRESIDENT Colleagues thank you
so much for your support for a
continuance last tuesday to
allow my team and I to meet
with the treasurer and tax
collectors office to explore
some amendments that would
allow the city to implement the
empty homes tax as soon as the
court allows while also
addressing the concerns of the
treasurer and tax collectors
office.
As I'm sure most of you know
this legislation is a
complicated one because the
voter approved empty homes tax
is being challenged by among
others the san francisco
apartment association and the
san francisco association of
realtors.
My biggest concern is what I
raised last week which is that
if the courts were to lift the
injunction at some point while
the litigation continued, this
legislation would prevent
collection of the tax until the
litigation is complete.
For those reasons I will be
voting no on today's ordinance.
As most of you know, we're in a
housing affordability crisis
and anti home tax was going to
be one of the many tools to
help alleviate these issues.
So many of our vacant units are
being used like shares of stock
in the stark stock market for
real estate investors to buy
them up and hold them for years
and then resell them at higher
values for profit.
And until housing is a human
right, we will continue to see
this.
I'm grateful for our city
attorney's efforts to overturn
the trial court's decision.
I will continue to follow this
case closely and look forward
to what I hope is a swift
resolution.
I also want to thank budget
chair chan and city in tax
collector and treasurer and tax
collector for engaging
in conversations.
supervisor walton thank you
so much PRESIDENT Melamed and
do we have anyone from the
department here to answer a
question?
I'm wondering if you I'm I
do not see anyone from the
treasury tax collector but we
could go on with the agenda and
come back to this and try to
get someone from the treasury
tax collector here to answer
your questions.
I think we should do that.
I do have a couple of questions
.
okay.
Maybe MR. Tong so that can
facilitate that put out a
request.
all right, great.
let's go to item.
Oh, okay.
Supervisor chan thank you,
PRESIDENT Man domain I I, I
wanted to say this I definitely
was a proponent of formally
known as proposition m to allow
us to collect this empty home
tax.
It was regrettable that to see
that right when we could
implement this to face this
lawsuit as a city it is my
understanding during the
committee and budget and
finance committee when we had
this discussion in good faith
definitely in an attempt to
work with supervisor fielder to
see what we can do to first and
foremost to be able to collect
this tax bill retroactively or
while the litigation is pending
as we now know you know, it's
not the most ideal as also
according to the budget
legislative analyst's report
that based on information that
we receive from the tax
collectors office about whether
that's possible to collect
while pending litigation which
we know the court has not
allowed but whether we can even
retroactive or however way we
can move forward, it is my
understanding that to do so
creates a burden and confusion
for the tax collectors office
so that the administrative
costs is greater than
potentially projected tax
collected.
So with that is the reason why
I will be supporting a
suspension of this collection
of this tax pending litigation
.
thank you.
thank you supervisor chan
with that we will come back to
item two and we have someone
from the treasurer's office.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item three?
Item number three is an
ordinance to appropriate
approximately $5 million of
state and federal revenues to
the human services agency for
direct client assistance,
rental subsidies and services
through the calworks housing
support program in fiscal year
2024 2025.
And pursuant to charter section
9.113 see this matter shall
require a vote of two thirds or
eight votes of the board of
supervisors.
I think we can take this item.
Same house, same call.
Without objection this
ordinance is passed on first
reading.
And then let's go back to item
two.
We have amanda freed conn.
hello.
Hi, good afternoon.
Supervisor is amanda kahn freed
from the office of the
treasurer and tax collector
supervisor on the first thank
you PRESIDENT Amanda thank you
because MADAM Minute thank you
amanda for being here.
one how much was the tax
estimated to yield?
I apologize supervisor I don't
have that in front of me right
now.
I don't know if there's a
colleague from the
comptroller's office that MAY
be able to answer that.
MR. Wagner sorry about that.
MR. Wagner.
I truly apologize.
as a supervisor I was in a
conversation.
Could you repeat the question?
how much is the was the
empty homes tax expected to you
each year?
it was approximately
estimated approximately 25
million $25 million in how much
money could we possibly be
leaving on the table with this
suspension?
uh uh depending on the
length of the suspension it
would be 25 times the number of
years that we're not collecting
the tax.
So depending on how long it
continues that would be the
math estimate it if I MAY add a
little bit to that answer.
one of the things I shared
in committee was that the cost
of collections while there is
legal uncertainty is much
higher.
So the empty homes tax similar
to the commercial vacancy tax
is an interesting construct for
a business tax because the
everyone who is required to
file has to every single year
submit to our office a
declaration, a tax filing about
whether or not their property
is vacant.
So for the empty homes tax it's
about 80,000 parcels that would
be subject to the tax, the vast
majority of which would not oh
the tax but still have to come
in and complete a filing so
similar to the commercial
vacancy tax we anticipate that
in the early years of the tax
the primary work that our
office is doing is taxpayer
communications and outreach to
make sure that everybody
understands their obligations
for the commercial vacancy tax.
As I've come and talked about
several times in chambers, the
first few years have been slow
on the revenue front but
expectedly slow because we have
to do our work to really make
sure that everyone who's
subject to the tax understands
their obligations and is filing
once that part is relatively
in order then we move to our
normal operations and
enforcement right to understand
who's lying, who's cheating,
who hasn't, who's trying to
hide from us.
That work takes some time.
so any time we have a novel
tax we expect there to be a
ramp up period.
But for a tax like this for the
empty homes tax where it's
primarily people who have never
paid a business tax to the city
and county for whom the entire
construct will be new.
We had budgeted an estimated
for a huge amount of work up
front on communications and
outreach which we were which
was well under way when there's
legal uncertainty that work
becomes much harder and so we
would need to spend more time
and effort to really reach out
to people to make sure that
they understand their
obligations to file this tax
and would anticipate much lower
revenues in the first few years
even if the case was settled we
would anticipate that and have
communicated that with the
comptroller's office but when
there still uncertainty would
be met we would expect it to be
even lower.
do we know what the amount
is in terms of the cost?
we haven't.
It's really impossible for us
to to estimate that we don't we
don't typically estimate that
but the cost for us to collect
we have talked about for
example some of the increased
costs during that time we would
have to probably triple our
communications.
So for 80,000 taxpayers every
mailing is quite expensive.
We would want to do several
hardcopy mailings.
We would want to do a paid
media campaign.
We would need to really develop
some very clear outreach
materials to make sure people
understood yes there is this
got this legal challenge going
on.
you're still required to
file and pay because there
would be a lot of uncertainty.
We would also given the legal
content constraints want to
make sure that anyone from our
office who is talking to
taxpayers while we had active
litigation going on was very
careful in what they said so we
would have a designated unit
that was highly trained and had
extra support from the city
attorney's office which would
of course also require more
resources just to make sure
that people were getting
accurate information and we
know whenever there's, you
know, a threat of litigation or
ongoing litigation that people
are often trying to trip up our
city workers.
so we want to protect
against that.
thank you and thank you to
the treasurer's office and
comptroller's office.
I just want to get some
clarity it'll be hard for me to
support so suspension of
collecting a tax particularly
during a time where we have 800
plus million dollar deficit and
I don't have the exact numbers
in terms of the cost benefit.
So I will be voting against
this as well.
thank you so much rest jim.
thank you.
Present amendment I my
apologies I don't mean to try
to correct the controllers here
but I would like to understand
the discrepancy between
projected $25 million and what
the budget and legislative
analyst in the report
indicating the estimated annual
annual revenue from the empty
home tax will be approximately
9 million for 20 in 2024 and
increasing to approximately
15.4 million in 2026 and beyond
.
I'm just trying to understand
the discrepancy between the 9
million and again 15.4 million
versus what the comptroller
comptroller wagner just
mentioned of 25 million no
projection at through the
PRESIDENT To chair shan thank
you for the opportunity to
correct that myself in the
budget and legislative analysts
we're just talking the 25
figure was from the original
comptrollers estimate in the
ballot handbook so as to
growing at 30 the 15 number
which is the annualized number
in the biela report reflects a
revision to essentially show
the potential impact of the tax
on the number of units that are
held vacant.
So if you're estimating a
market response to the tax you
MAY have fewer units vacant.
So the 15.6 is a revised sized
estimate and I would advise you
to use that revised estimate
the census developed later than
our original ballot estimate.
thank you.
All right.
Thank you, supervisor chand
singh.
No one else in the queue.
MADAM Clerk, please call the
roll on item two an item two
supervisor sadr.
Sadr I supervisor sherril
sherril I supervisor walton I
mean no walton.
no supervisor chen I chen I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder no supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor mandolin
mandolin I supervisor melgar I
melgar I there are nine eyes
and two nose with supervisors
walton infielder voting no all
right this ordinance is passed
on first reading MADAM Clerk
can you please call items four
and five together?
yes items four and five
comprise two airport leases.
Item four is a resolution to
approve modification number
three to the lease between the
us, united states of america
and the city acting through its
airport commission to extend
the term by three years for a
new term ending JANUARY 3rd,
2028 and increase the annual
rent to approximately 960,000
totaling approximately 2.9
million.
And item five is a resolution
to authorize a third amendment
to the lease between michael c
mitchell and the city acting by
and through its airport
commission extending the lease
term for three years for a
total term of APRIL 21st 22,009
through APRIL 30th two 2028 and
increasing the annual rent to
159,000 for use by the san
francisco international airport
repro graphics department at
837 malcolm road burlingame
please call the roll on these
items and items four and five
supervisor sartor sadr I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan I chan I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio and
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor mandolin
hi mendelson I supervisor
melgar I melgar I there are
lebanese these resolutions are
adopted MADAM Clerk can you
please call item six through
nine together?
yes item six through nine
comprise four resolutions
approving the first amendments
to contracts for the purchase
of information technology
products and specialized
services on an as needed basis
under the technology
marketplace program.
These contract agreements are
between the city acting through
the office of contract
administration and various
entities when no changes to the
five year terms.
Item six is a resolution to
approve the contract amendment
with isis is squared inc doing
business as computer land of
silicon valley to increase the
amount by approximately 41
million for a not to exceed
amount of approximately 61
million.
Item seven is a resolution to
approve the contract amendment
with cornerstone technology
partners to jayvee to increase
the amount by approximately 22
million for a not to exceed
amount of approximately 42
million.
Item eight is a resolution to
approve the contract with
insite public sector inc to
increase the amount by
approximately 434 million for a
not to exceed amount of
approximately 54 million.
And item nine is a resolution
to approve the contract
amendment with ex tex x tech g
h I x tech doing business as
eaton associates 21 tech llc to
increase the amount by
approximately 65 million for a
not to exceed amount of
approximately 85 million.
thank you MADAM MADAM clerk
,I think we can take these
items same house, same call
without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
and then can you please call
items ten and 27 together?
Yes.
Item ten is an ordinance
authorizing settlement of the
lawsuit filed by hotel day arts
llc against the city that
challenges the 2020 three
amendments to the residential
hotel unit conversion and
demolition ordinance with the
material terms of the
settlement requiring the city
to permit the conversion of the
existing 38 residential hotel
rooms at 447 bush street to
tourists hotel rooms
in exchange for the conversion
of 27 group housing rooms and
associated amenities at 412 to
422 hayes and seven group
housing rooms and associated
amenities at 319 to 321 ivy
street to residential hotel
rooms.
And item 27 was considered by
the land use and transportation
committee at a regular meeting
on MARCH 17th, 2022 at five and
it was recommended to the full
board as a committee report.
It is a ordinance amending the
planning code to principally
permit up to 51 tourist hotel
rooms at 447 bush street.
Exempting a conditional use
authorization and waiving
development impact fees and
requirements and making
appropriate findings.
All right.
I think we can take these items
same house, same call without
objection these ordinances are
passed on first reading MADAM
Clerk, can you please call item
number 11?
item number 11 is a
resolution authorizing the
recreation and parks department
and various staff within the
mayor's office to solicit
donations for the renovation of
embarcadero plaza and sue
beerman parks from individuals,
nonprofits and private
organizations, grant makers and
foundations for six months from
the effective date of this
resolution notwithstanding the
be tested payment ordinance.
supervisor fielder thank you
PRESIDENT Colleagues, I have
have was a part of
conversations as chair of on
an oversight committee to
recommend and this has said
payment waivers there are a
number of hazard payment
waivers coming before us and
committee but I just wanted to
make some points about.
About you know, the reason for
the hazard payment waivers were
designed to ensure that
companies doing business with
the city couldn't influence
officials through donations to
favored causes and without a
waiver and recology was at the
center of what the department
of justice called one of the
largest corruption scandals
in san francisco history.
just as a general this is
not pertaining just to this
specific waiver but recology as
a company admitted to directing
hundreds of thousands in bribes
to city officials in exchange
for favorable business outcomes
and since then recology has
undertaken significant
leadership changes including a
new ceo and substantial board
turnover along with
implementing doj reforms.
And I fully support the
renovation of embarcadero
plaza, suburban park, a lot of
other infrastructure projects
coming before us in the city
and I also want to remind
everyone that we have to ensure
we maintain the highest ethical
standards and we will be
continuing to do just that in
on an oversight committee
making sure that these waivers
are narrowed to only those who
specifically need to have them
and also requiring regular
reporting.
thank you all so much.
Marisa dorsey thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandolin I wanted to
add my name to the roster both
to associate myself with
supervisor fielder's points and
to underscore that while I'm
happy to support this behest
and payments waiver we are
in no way retreating from the
principles of public integrity
that motivated the enactment of
behest and payments
restrictions in the first
place.
I think especially in the era
we're in with core functions of
our federal being dismantled
by the trump administration and
doge those of us who believe
in what good can accomplish
need to be more vigilant than
ever to avoid not just the
corruption scandals we've seen
in recent years obviously but
to avoid even the appearance of
conflicts of and pay to play
schemes when the city
attorney's office initiated its
public corruption case against
recology I wasn't in the office
at that time but I did spend 14
years working with former city
attorney dennis herrera and I
learned firsthand how important
public integrity work is.
So I'm grateful that recology
has by all accounts reformed
its practices.
But I did want to express my
hope that we will always be
wise and prudent in how we make
use of these waivers whenever
they're granted.
Thank you.
Supervisor dorsey seeing no one
else in the queue I think we
can take this item.
Oh there we go.
Now we have the same house.
I think we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
And MADAM Clerk, can you please
call items 12 and 13 together?
yes.
Item number 12 is an ordinance
amending the general plan to
reduce commercial development
requirements in the central
soma area plan and the transit
center districts subarea plan
areas and making appropriate
findings.
And item 13 is an ordinance
amending the planning code and
zoning map to reduce commercial
development requirements for
certain residential projects
and modify the land dedication
requirements in the central
soma special use district and
remove the transit center for
commercial special use district
and making appropriate
findings.
supervisor dorsey thank you
PRESIDENT Mandolin colleagues
i'll be brief on this.
I did want to express my
excitement for this legislative
practice package that
reimagines two key areas of
downtown while staying true to
the values and principles of
the central soma plan.
Through this package we are
opening up central soma and the
transit district to more
residential development while
retaining key community
benefits that were negotiated
many years ago.
Opening up these areas will
play a key role in meeting our
housing targets and spurring
economic activity in downtown.
I'm really proud of the broad
consensus that we have built on
these changes and I want to
thank the planning commission
and planning director hillis
for their thoughtful oversight
and work on this to ensure that
the long promised community
benefits like complete streets,
parks and recreation will still
be delivered.
I also want to thank the mayor
for his partnership and his
office the incredible joint
development team at twd and
topia and jacob bentley's
especially.
I also want to thank members of
the development nonprofit labor
communities that spoke
in support of this and thanks
as well to madison tam from my
office for her work.
I want to thank my colleagues
finally and I look forward to
having the support in passing
these items today.
thanks so much.
All right.
I think we can take these items
same house, same call without
objection these ordinances are
passed on first reading.
and MADAM Clerk, will you
please call item number 14?
I don't remember.
14 is an ordinance accepting
irrevocable offers of public
infrastructure associated with
the treasure island yerba buena
island project for the bruton's
sanitary sewer pump station.
The kravis sanitary sewer pump
station the mcallen sanitary
sewer pump station and the
northgate sanitary sewer pump
station and making appropriate
findings.
all right.
I think we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection this ordinance is
passed on first reading and
MADAM Clerk let's go to our
2:30 P.M. Special order our 230
special orders recognition of
commendations and let's start
with supervisor sauder,
district three.
Thank you, PRESIDENT Gentlemen
,colleagues, as many of you
know, we are in the midst of
celebrating women's history
month and today is also transit
operators day.
So in recognition of both these
important celebrations, I'm
proud to recognize two
outstanding women employees
from S.F. Mta today will
johnson and wish only both of
these women are to be
celebrated for all of their
work each day where they show
up and alongside other
operators maintenance and
security staff, ambassadors and
engineers work hard to keep san
francisco moving.
In particular, I want to thank
them both for keeping district
three moving and I'd first like
to speak on willa johnson.
Willa is a tremendous treasure
in san francisco so our cable
cars are important and willa is
even more important.
Willa has been a operator since
she joined us from in 1999 and
she is just the second woman
grip person at the cable car
division.
She has been and continues to
be an inspiration to not just
her fellow women coworkers but
to all the women who see her
doing her job whether they be
residents or travelers from
around the world who love our
cable cars and get to meet
willa well wells hobbies
include decorating and using
her creativity to make spaces
more beautiful and inviting.
I'm happy to honor willow's
dedication and her positive
spirit that make her an
incredible part of san
francisco.
Thank you all.
And I would invite you if you'd
like to say a few words.
Thank you.
it is an honor and a
pleasure and I really
appreciate the recognition and
just to say thank you.
I would like to recognize as
you wish only your wish only or
wendy began working with S.F.
Mta in 2015 meaning she will
celebrate almost ten years of
service.
She will celebrate ten years of
service soon.
Wendy works mostly out of
kirkland yard which services
our northeast corners of san
francisco and lays
in fisherman's wharf.
wendy is the mother of
newborn twins whom she loves
very much and outside of work
when she's not taking care of
our city and our transit
riders, she loves to exercise
and to shop.
And when asked about
encountering difficult
situations in her work, she
offered these words of wisdom
be patient, smile and always
try to stay in control of your
emotions.
As are good words for all of us
to live by.
So thank you andy, for your
wonderful personality, your
dedication to your work and all
of your service to san
francisco.
And I would love to invite you
to say a few words as well if
you'd like.
I'm happy here today.
I just want to say thank you
everyone.
I enjoy working with mta a no,
not just like your family does
work in your reservoir so I can
take care of my twin baby and
can I?
I can help the passenger every
day so I hear different story.
So I feel like I'm part of the
community by helping the
passenger to their destination
safety.
yeah.
thank you.
You are going to get it.
Okay.
Thank you, whitney.
Thank you.
Okay.
District five supervisor
mahmood or you need to get
your.
All right.
Should we go to seven district
seven supervisor melgar?
okay.
all right.
Colleagues, I'm hoping that my
honorees are here already.
oh, yes, they are.
Thank you so much.
And in honor of women's history
month, I am proud to stand to
recognize at three remarkable
women who are the sworn
officers who serve on the
leadership of the S.F. Pd.
Right now we have at acting
deputy chief at rachel moran,
commander nicole jones and
acting commander alexa o'brien.
and we have a commander
o'brien here today at these
women exemplify dedication,
excellence and the critical
role women play in shaping the
future of law enforcement today
.
We have a commander o'brien
here who will be accepting this
recognition on behalf of her
colleagues at commander o'brien
leads the special victims unit
overseeing complex and
sensitive investigations
involving sexual assaults and
crimes against vulnerable
members of our community.
Her rise through the ranks from
police officer to command staff
is a testament to her
leadership, integrity and
unwavering commitment to
justice and public service.
She not only leads within the
department but also actively
engages in our community and
media to raise awareness and
build trust.
Commander o'brien's path to
leadership is deeply rooted
in san francisco.
Born at the former children's
hospital on california street.
she spent her early childhood
in the avenues before
relocating to new york with her
mother in 1984.
the strong bond to her
hometown brought her back to
attend the university of san
francisco where she earned a
bachelor of science
in sociology with a minor
in criminology.
After completing her degree,
she began her career in public
service as a clerk to mayor
brown and thereafter joined the
S.F. Pd in 2000.
Her earliest shipments took her
to southern to mission to
northern stations and also
served as a school car officer
in the mission district.
She later served as the street
sergeant at ingleside station
before transitioning to station
investigations.
Commander o'brien steadily rose
through the ranks managing the
night investigation units.
Now seiu and the homicide
division as a lieutenant and
in 2016 she was promoted to
captain.
Her leadership journey within
the S.F. Pd has been marked by
dedication and a deep
commitment to the safety and
well-being of our community.
thank you.
I also want to recognize the
exceptional careers of cmdr.
nicole jones who currently
leads the mta division within
the S.F. Pd.
commander jones has served
across the city beginning her
career at tenderloin and
ingleside stations.
That's where I met her because
she was at one of our captains
and as a sergeant she worked
in the special victims unit and
internal affairs criminal
investigations.
As a lieutenant she held key
administrative roles in the
chief's office and staffing and
deployment units and also
served as a patrol lieutenant
at northern station as captain
at ingleside station and after
her promotion to commander she
was assigned to the
administration bureau.
her wide ranging experience
and leadership are truly
inspiring.
And last but not least while
acting deputy chief moran could
not be with us today either, I
want to take a moment to
highlight her distinguished
service as well commander
marine currently leads the
investigations bureau and is
one of the highest ranking
sworn officers in women in S.F.
Pd with over 25 years of
experience in service.
she has held numerous
pivotal roles.
In FEBRUARY of 2021 she was
appointed captain of mission
station becoming the first
woman in decades to lead that
station a tenure marked by
strong community engagement and
a focus on neighborhood safety.
Nine months later she was
promoted to commander and she
now serves as acting deputy
chief of investigations, a
critical bureau supporting
victims and advancing criminal
cases citywide.
her dedication to public
service and community
connections exemplifies the
very best of leadership in law
enforcement.
so on behalf of district
seven and the city and county
of san francisco, I want to
extend my heartfelt thanks to
these outstanding women for
their service your courage,
your leadership and your
commitment to justice make our
city strong or in you also pave
the way for others.
You are just paving the way for
future generations of women to
lead and serve with
distinction.
I also want to thank
district seven resident deputy
chief eleazar for being here
assistant chief last hour for
being here today.
We are grateful for your
presence and also always your
support.
chief scott was not able to
be with us today because of a
public town hall meeting that
was scheduled at the same time.
But he expressed his support
for these wonderful officers.
Thank you all.
thank you for being here and
happy women's history month and
hold up because supervisor
dorsey would like to say
something.
thank you.
Just a.
I first want to applaud
supervisor melgar for who is an
exceptional woman in her own
right for a great choice and
for some great remarks to honor
these exceptional women
officers.
They were my former colleagues
in the san francisco police
department.
I am a big fan of all the
honorees but since she is here
in chambers I did want to
express my gratitude to acting
commander alexa o'brien for her
work on 21st century police
reform which I think too often
goes unheralded.
It was the reason that I wanted
to work for chief of police
bill scott in the S.F. Pd when
I joined that department.
Five years ago commander
o'brien worked on use of force
reform and san francisco has
been particularly influential
at the national level for that
category of police reform.
In 2017 san francisco was the
first city in the nation to
enact all eight of the eight
can't wait use of force policy
reforms.
For those of you who don't
know, eight can't wait or the
use of force reforms that the
national organization campaign
zero advocated for.
That included things like
de-escalation, banning
chokeholds, the duty to
intervene, comprehensive
reporting and more.
San francisco led the nation on
that.
Today 20 major cities have
followed san francisco's lead.
In no small part for the work
done by the san francisco
police department including
commander o'brien.
so thank you so much for
that work.
now you're up, commander.
Oh, thank you so much.
supervisor melgar and all of
the board of supervisors.
I just want to thank you for
the attention that you've
brought to women in the
policing.
I've been in 25 years and
I've never had so much
recognition and it's just
wonderful because we are
in desperate need of police
officers and women especially
and I just think this is a
great opportunity to tell the
women of the city how amazing
as a pd is and to work for them
and it's a great job and I
challenge women to come in.
It's a lot of fun.
and thank you.
Thank you.
On behalf of the dc and also
commander nicole jones.
thank you.
Thank you.
And I think you want to say a
few.
supervisor melgar, I just
want to thank you on behalf of
chief scott and the entire
department for this incredible
recognition.
And I also want to thank
PRESIDENT Randleman and the
board who came to 50 years of
history 50 years of women
in the S.F. Pd as we celebrated
that during women's history
month.
It was incredible.
Thank you all for your support.
I see director approaches here
from the department as well.
Thank you.
Thank you so you you were my
neighbor.
You you.
next up district nine
supervisor fielder thank you,
PRESIDENT Colleagues, I'm
thrilled to present this
special commendation today
during women's history month to
honor a group of women who
demonstrate the best
in leadership and community
organizing.
12 women who are founders of
nuevo sol de labor and domestic
worker center and are here with
us today to receive this
special honor.
and as soon as the nuevo sol
last quito recognized pursue a
tremendous trabajo and a
community then nuevo sol was
formed last year emerging from
an effort to organize community
members around the needs of day
laborers and domestic workers
in san francisco.
Many of their members have more
than 30 years of experience
working as and organizing with
the domestic workers and day
laborers of san francisco.
and their strength,
dedication, commitment led to
the founding of nuevo sol four
from their mission statement
they quote empower and uplift
day laborers and domestic
workers in san francisco and
the surrounding region
fostering a thriving local
economy that is built on mutual
respect, fairness and community
relations.
chips with a brick and
mortar office located
in district nine at 2973 16th
street nuevo sol also operates
a mobile office every thursday
and saturday from 7 to 10 A.M.
At the corner of 26th and
harrison.
They want us they want to make
sure that every neighbor in the
city of san francisco and
throughout the region who needs
skilled labor knows that this
collective of workers has so
much to offer.
they are here to provide
excellent services to meet all
kinds of labor needs
in addition to providing
services and skilled labor.
nuevo sol has a long term
vision.
they want neighbors to know
that they too are part of the
fabric of our vibrant community
and that together we can all
build a local economy that
works for everyone.
Their motto is a rising tide
lifts all boats level all can
meet labor needs and match them
with those hiring in exchange
for a living wage.
Workplaces that guarantee the
health and safety of workers
and foster mutual respect and
accountability.
This wonderful group of woman
leaders hopes to nourish this
relationship with every
neighbor in san francisco and
surrounding region in order to
build a better city where all
can flourish.
Gracias.
For instance, those same
heroines bolero says puerto
rico and west are coming from
elle.Com you know vienna
neither I arriba neither is the
one that's pedro vina.
The the leader as my head is
going with status the lisi that
is a mean gracious person as
far as what those e be that go
following us today me number
three categories.
Good afternoon.
My name is erica chavez so you
live it leader de novo sol I'm
a leader and it was all day
labor domestic worker center so
you started ballerina
in miranda murillo has that
organizers I'm salvadoran.
I immigrated to the united
states but other than my her be
that amiga so that I could give
a better life to my daughter
gang gangster of basal
condition that the virus only
difficiles because in our
country life is very very
difficult your trabalho duro so
mujer trabajadores yeah I'm a
hard working woman.
Delgado quedo ninos olympia
casas I care for children.
I clean homes but I maintain
I'm here.
my mother and I do this
in order to support my mother
and my daughter.
giacomo mujer MS. Santamaria
kompromat either.
as a woman I feel very
committed but I can see her
como mujeres professional so
that my daughter become a
professional.
is this to the opera doctora
she's currently studying to be
a doctor.
I MISS Yentl my own rather
to me companero leader this
person recognizes us today I
feel very honored together with
my partner your workers
companions here who are also
leaders for this recognition
eradication colony strong new
organization.
we are deeply dedicated to
our organization as a new
organization cannot complacency
are game that militated remain
a seamless which was reborn
in 20 2023 entrepreneurs aida
de la muerte the latin latina
immigrants again it became a
reality due to the needs of our
workers latina immigrants not
of opera la lucha per col soto
la muerte s by someone much as
discrimination is we cannot
stop our struggle because we
women suffer discrimination our
cause of sexual and sexual
harassment la falta de la lack
of equality la falta justicia
lack of justice la faltering
neither lack of dignity by some
appearances domestic we suffer
domestic violence grow as
alario wage theft a new assault
animal health compromise so to
say it luciano in nervous all
day labor domestic workers
center we have the commitment
to continue the struggle paulo
derecha de la muerte is
trabajadores for the rights of
working women the longer it
allows more hatred echolocate
somos la maladie criminal us
and for the rights of all
working women of color who are
the most discriminated.
mother teresa amiel
trabajadores de la nota and
then protects you on the salary
so would you go over 300,000
domestic workers have no safety
for protections for health and
safety an nosotros uppermost
importance and that's why we
organize.
we support and empower.
I was going to point though
sorry that it was so
immigration and that's why we
do this in support of
immigration rights and and our
worker rights.
nosotros la muerte es so
more intelligent this vision
era for the people there shows
us we women are visionaries.
we're strong and we're
powerful grasshopper
recognizing mental cleansing.
Thank you for this recognition
is disappointing and yes we can
well shakira's yes my might not
district ten supervisor walton
thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Colleagues today in recognition
of women's history month I am
excited to honor azeri peace
green a remarkable leader
advocate and force for change
in san francisco as there is
life is a testament to
resilience, love and unwavering
dedication to community
service.
A proud san francisco native
she has transformed personal
hardship into a lifelong
commitment to uplifting others
as the executive director of
community awareness resource
entity, also known as care, a
nonprofit founded by her
husband donald green, azari has
worked tirelessly to support
and empower those in need.
Her leadership is informed by
lived experience having
overcome homelessness and
addiction.
She now serves as a beacon of
hope for countless individuals
navigating similar struggles.
Her advocacy extends far beyond
care.
Zuri has dedicated herself to
community safety and justice
serving on the bayview station
community police advisory
board, the san francisco police
department procedural justice
education team and the police
chiefs african american
advisory council.
Her voice and lived experience
have played a crucial role
in shaping equitable policies
and practices.
In addition, her work and
commitment to community
enrichment shines through her
work with the friends of
jackson park and into action
ensuring that our neighborhoods
thrive for generations to come
as there is achievements are
many including earning a B.A.
In human service management and
a master's in public
administration.
yet perhaps her greatest legacy
is the family she has built
eight children, 16
grandchildren, two great
grandchildren all of whom are
undoubtedly inspired by her
strength and perseverance
grounded in faith and
community, azaria's journey
embodies the power of second
chances, the strength of
service and the balance impact
of a woman determined to make a
difference.
Her openness, wisdom and
passion continue to shape a
more just and compassionate san
francisco.
I want to extend my deepest
gratitude to missouri for her
unwavering commitment to
justice equity and community
empowerment.
Your leadership continues to be
an inspiration to us all.
thank you.
I just want to say thank you
very much.
I first given it a GOD
because without him I wouldn't
be able to do this.
And I think my mom is georgia
ri because she man she has gone
through so much and she embody
me and empowered me.
I thank my husband.
We got married a month and a
half after we met and we
celebrated 25 years and I
really thank my partner our
whole community the community
as at me sat down and worked
with me and I thank those that
had just given me the honor to
be able to be a voice and I
thank you.
Supervisor walton for always
being there for community.
I thank all the supervisors
and I think those who allow
those who do not have a voice
to uplift their voice.
and so I want to cry.
thank you very, very much
for this honor because I did
not see this one coming.
But I just am very, very
appreciative for everything
that I'm the higher power
allows me to be able to do and
community for community and
with community.
Thank you to supervisor mahmood
.
go for it today it is an
absolute honor to recognize
some true champions among us
here in the chambers the
international school of san
francisco jaguars.
because when I come up here
it's it's a momentous day as
the san francisco jaguars last
weekend for the first time ever
became state championships
winners in all of california
since its founding in 1962.
The international school of san
francisco has fostered a
culture of excellence both
in the classroom and on the
court.
this championship win is a
testament to the dedication and
perseverance instilled in its
students from an early age a
testament to the power of what
we can achieve through teamwork
and camaraderie.
this year's varsity
basketball team exemplifies
that grit, resilience and heart
from their pcl central league
championship to their north cal
title.
And now the ultimate prize
state champions.
This team has inspired our city
with the determination and
teamwork.
senior captain and league
mvp connor mcguire led the team
with an unforgettable
performance including a
legendary 63 point game.
round of applause for that.
his leadership alongside the
relentless drive of every
player brought this team to the
top in the championship game.
the jaguars overcame a 12
point deficit in the second
half showcasing their
resilience and determination.
Connor mcguire's 35 point
performance including a crucial
three pointer in the final
minutes, was instrumental
in securing that victory as
well.
but success like this
doesn't happen by chance.
It's built over years of
dedication and mentorship.
A huge congratulations to coach
paul cortez who has led this
program for the past nine
years.
And to his fellow coaches
alumnus vince sutton and city
native dario cadeau for their
commitment to shaping our youth
into not just great athletes
but great leaders.
coach paul is known in the
san francisco youth basketball
community as a coach who values
preparation, focus, respect,
teamwork and fun.
Whether he's coaching third
graders in their inaugural
tournament or leading a team of
high schoolers to their state
championship, this win is
bigger than basketball.
it represents our san
francisco values values of hard
work, perseverance and the
power of believing in yourself
and one another.
the jaguars have shown that
with determination, confidence
and teamwork anything is
possible.
this victory brings immense
pride to our city and we
celebrate this team not only
for their championship title
but for the values they uphold.
Sportsmanship, resilience and
community spirit.
we're joined today by
coaches paul cortez, vincent,
an athletic director sara
shaughnessy and david henriquez
,high school principal allegra
molyneux, head of school DR.
Melinda beane, carolyn
oberstar.
he sometimes here and the
champions themselves.
On behalf of the board of
supervisors, congratulations to
the international school of the
san francisco jaguars.
Their coaches, their families
and the entire school on this
historic achievement.
you have made san francisco
proud.
on behalf of the san
francisco board of supervisors
and our mayor daniel lurie,
we're here to present you with
a basketball not not just some
flowers all signed by us as
well.
good afternoon, everyone.
Thank you for hosting us today.
supervisor mahmood board of
supervisors.
On behalf of the international
school of san francisco, I am
honored to accept this
commendation and celebrate what
has truly been a historic
achievement for our school
in our city as international is
only the sixth school to win
this coveted championship.
The state championship isn't
just about our trophy it
represents many years of
dedication, perseverance and
teamwork.
Many of our students have been
with us since pre-k growing up
within this community and it
has been such a privilege for
us to watch them develop into
the exceptional student
athletes, leaders and humans
that they are today.
I also want to recognize our
coaching staff led by coach
paul cortez whose leadership
over the past nine years has
shaped this program into
something truly special.
And thank you to coach dario
and coach events who came back
as an alumna and returned to
help guide this team to
greatness.
the next generation of
jaguars and of course our
players who showed incredible
grit, resilience and heart
especially in the biggest
moments when it mattered the
most.
Time and time again our jaguars
came from behind in critical
games and never back down from
a challenge.
I'd also like to shout out
our athletics office for their
dedication behind the scenes so
our associate ed david
henriquez thank you for
everything that you do from
taping ankles to planning team
dinners, rescheduling games and
making sure that our charter
busses are actually on time.
your hard work made the
season run seamlessly to ian
and joey who aren't here today
but they start the foundation
of our program in third grade
athletics and because of them
and the impact they have
in teaching students the love
for the game is why we're so
strong.
And also joey gets all of our
amazing photos so make sure to
check those out on their
instagram.
None of this would have been
possible without our amazing
leadership team.
Thank you to melinda, ben and
alexa and our mccombs team for
believing in this team's
potential and allowing us to
support them in every way
possible.
But beyond the wins and the
records, what made this team
truly special was the
brotherhood and the camaraderie
that they've built.
this was a team that played
for each other, supported one
another and embraced challenges
together.
The bond was the formation of
their success and what I hope
lives the longest in their
memories.
what made this championships
the best the most special for
us was that we brought our
entire school sixth through
12th grade to golden one center
and watched them make history.
seeing our students,
faculty, families in the stands
cheering us on was a moment
that none of us will ever
forget.
This is not just a victory for
our team but a victory for our
entire school and the city of
san francisco.
the championship we hope is
just one chapter in our
beautiful story and it hopes to
still get written and I
couldn't be more proud to say
go jags to captain go ahead
that I'm so I say a couple
words I mean I'd say thank you
for this award.
I mean that's all I really got
today but I'm vocal
in welcoming wil to the silver
.
Yeah thanks for having us.
I mean this team really means a
lot to me and I'm really glad
we're being recognized for all
the hard work we put in.
And I'm really glad that all
the work we put in over these
past few years really paid off.
that's all I got to say.
congratulations, patrick.
Patrick the I don't feel
district to supervisor sherril
.
colleagues today I'm
recognizing the heritage on the
marina upon its 100th
anniversary at the corner of
bay in laguna heritage on the
marina was originally founded
by the san francisco ladies
protection and relief society
in 1853 with a mission to aid
women and children before
evolving into a care home for
san francisco's elderly
residents in the early 20th
century.
Now in 1922 the society
commissioned the trailblazing
architect julia morgan to
design and construct the elder
care facility at the corner of
bay and laguna.
That is a beautiful, beautiful
brick building that the
heritage still calls home today
since the facility's opening
in 1925, the heritage has been
committed to serving the needs
of seniors with both
independent and assisted living
arrangements.
I recently toured the facility
and I was astounded by the
care, the community and frankly
the serenity that the heritage
residents that the heritage
offers its elderly residents.
But in addition to serving its
residents, the leadership team
of heritage has remained
dedicated to preserving the
rich legacy of the women who
built and sustained this key
city resource.
I am extremely grateful for the
stewardship of ceo mary lundy
who goes above and beyond for
the residents knowing each one
taking the time to make every
resident feel like family.
But beyond that care mary has
also been a very prudent leader
of the facility working
tirelessly to to sustain
heritage operations and to
ensure this long standing
pillar of community care
remains at bay in laguna for
another century.
But it's not just mary and her
team that makes heritage so
special.
It's the residents too.
And margaret, every community
needs a leader.
margaret chico's energy and
passion for her friends and
neighbors is just so evident
when you look into her eyes
when you hear her talk.
They are so lucky to have a
ringleader or oh wait no I
should say a strong leader like
you.
I can't wait for the party
on the 27th.
so with that I'd like to
offer my deep congratulations
for hitting this milestone.
and I'd love you to perhaps to
come to the podium and offer a
few remarks.
congratulations.
thank you.
okay.
Well, the best decision I ever
made in my life was 24 years
ago without knowing really what
I was getting into.
I moved into heritage.
I've always been believer
that community is the essence
of life.
I've raised my family that
way in cooperatives all through
my adult life.
And truly the heritage has been
a perfect example of how that
community brings about health,
happiness and a group of people
that you cannot imagine showed
the compassion and care for
each other at the same time.
We're having a great time.
So thank you.
supervisor sherril thank you
so much.
I want to point out a few other
people who are here with me.
I have my board chair randy
gridley, another board member
and resident tony hanley and
julia morgan, historian and
resident tayo armer.
Two new residents jim and candy
norton and a resident nancy as
a good morning.
But the heritage isn't just a
building.
Julia morgan built this
building for women and children
who were abandoned to their
husbands and fathers who left
during the gold rush.
And when she built the building
it was built with a lot of
symbols and one of those
symbols was the tudor rose and
the tudor rose as a symbol of
love and compassion.
And one of the great things and
margaret just said it is that
that's what we do inside that
building we love and serve one
another.
We we as staff serve each other
.
We as staff serve the
residents.
The board governs and serves us
but it's done with love and
care and compassion.
I often say the work we do
isn't really care it's love
because if we're not caring
from our hearts it doesn't
really communicate.
And I think margaret summed it
up best when she said we are
truly a community of people who
love each other and who are
thriving.
These are not people who are
just dying.
These are people who are living
really well and thriving and
living beautifully.
so thank you so much for
this honor.
I'm looking for this place.
You know, look
.
Do you have anything to say?
hello.
It's good to see you.
all right.
district eight betsy eddy.
Come on up.
colleagues, it is my great
honor to present a special
commendation to betsy eddy who
prior to stepping down
in FEBRUARY had served as
PRESIDENT Of the diamond
heights community association
for 16 years.
betsy moved to san francisco
49 years ago.
She was born in cincinnati,
ohio and raised in kentucky.
Her early experiences
volunteering for her church
amidst violent threats and
working with low income
children ignited her passion
for service.
After witnessing the 1970 kent
state shootings as a young
college student, she went on to
earn her bachelor's in fine
arts from kent state university
in 1971 and eventually earned a
master's in family and consumer
services in 1986 from wayne
state university.
after graduating from
college, betsy joined
volunteers and service to
america.
This star she worked as a
community organizer providing
social services and recreation
programs for young children
in the small segregated town of
canton mint, florida.
after moving to san
francisco, betsy worked
in theater nonprofits and
eventually went to work for the
city addressing the needs of
aging san franciscans and
unhoused families for 21 years
before she retired in 2013.
but for betsy, retirement
did not mean slowing down.
Betsy was just getting started
.
She has been the consummate
neighbor leader and I know
colleagues you know this type
of person.
She has worked closely with
three district eight
supervisors me, jeff sheehy and
scott wiener.
and she has made us all
better at our jobs.
nine years ago betsy worked
with her membership to develop
the diamond heights community
association priority list, an
annual to do list for the
district eight office.
As it relates to diamond
heights, that priority list has
led to the installation of stop
signs paved sidewalks along
diamond heights boulevard and a
crosswalk with ross crosswalk
with blinking lights to make
the street a little safer for
pedestrians on their way to the
shopping center.
But that's just like a tiny
chunk of or a tiny number of
the items that have we've
worked on on that list.
bathrooms and and so many
lighting and tennis courts and
so many so many projects.
in addition to her service
with the hca, betsy helped
found resilient diamond
heights, a neighborhood group
that provides training and
resources and guides the
neighborhood's planning and
preparation for emergencies.
And she was also a founding
member of the diamond heights
boulevard median project that
has transformed the medians
along four long blocks from a
wasteland of weeds and
dead shrubs to a beautiful
corridor by installing new
plants and trees and
maintaining the stretch with
volunteers and grants.
diamond diamond heights has
been fortunate beyond measure
to have betsy leading to the
hca.
And so have I and my staff.
Her dedication and leadership
have made diamond heights safer
and more connected and more
resilient community.
And as I said, she has made me
a better supervisor.
betsy.
From the bottom of my heart I
thank you.
we thank you.
And the floor is yours.
Oh, thank you.
good afternoon, everyone.
And thank you, PRESIDENT
Randleman.
what an honor that you chose
to commend me.
out of all the remarkable
volunteers and district eight
the women volunteers on behalf
of all the community groups and
diamond heights we give you a
huge hugs and huge thanks for
all you've done for our
neighborhood.
I am honored that the
commendation is for women's
history month.
my young adult years were
influenced by women's lib
outwith the make up bras,
skirts and in with birth
control or having a credit card
in my own name without a male
cosigner.
And more women in leadership
roles.
it was awesome for me to
hear shirley chisholm address
the board of supervisors right
here about 40 years ago.
my parents and siblings were
my role models for volunteering
but it was the kent state
massacre that changed my life
toward a life of service for
students were killed and nine
seriously wounded in an
unwarranted shooting by the
ohio national guard in the
parking lot outside my dorm.
I wanted to speak about this
since many younger people do
not know about the tragedy and
how the killings gave momentum
to ending the vietnam war.
diamond heights was
developed as a model community
in the 1960s and 70s with our
glorious views winding streets
for parks, housing for all
income levels and cute
including 640 units of
affordable housing.
Diamond heights is a lovely lee
neighborhood but still has too
many speeding drivers who think
stop signs are optional.
diamond heights has a
another dangerous problem.
many of the monterey cypress
and pine trees are over 50
years old and are dropping
heavy branches laden with pine
cones on sidewalks and medians.
please provide more funding
for faster response by the
bureau of urban forestry to
deal with dangerous tree issues
and fixing sidewalks cracked by
tree roots creating tripping
hazards.
we have many other concerns
throughout the years but as a
PRESIDENT Man on land said the
many supervisors have helped us
most.
all the volunteer tier work
I did was with community
organizations in the
neighborhood.
any successes could not have
been achieved alone.
The diamond heights community
center has been the main
platform for advocating for
infrastructure improvements and
park remodels.
I owe thanks to our current
board members betty peskin bob
pulliam, cliff dietz, daniel
sharrock, denise garrity lee
and privacy and puja sabu raul
daniel and denise to our new
PRESIDENT And vice PRESIDENT.
both will revive allies our
association PRESIDENT Man woman
thank you for your tremendous
support for resilient diamond
heights.
The first neighborhood
resiliency group in san
francisco PRESIDENT Manuel
mandolin then we are so
grateful that you convened a
town hall and titled fire
mitigation in our neighborhood
parks in SEPTEMBER 2018.
emergency responders and rec
and park staff all said they
could handle any fire and glen
canyon park are resilient.
diamond heights steering
committee composed of cynthia
wu.
Daniel sharrock david lasker,
ed schaffner, greg kerry, jill
brecker and I think that in our
dry months on a very windy day
a fire could cause eucalyptus
trees to explode and spend and
spread embers quickly to the
entire park and to surrounding
neighborhoods as in the
wildfires and pacific palisades
and altadena.
resilient diamond heights
continues to advocate to remove
dry fuel from our four parks
and diamond heights to prevent
an urban wildfire.
as you talked about our
reunion project, we're very
proud of that.
It's a point six miles along
diamond heights boulevard and
with our monthly volunteer days
community challenge grants and
eagle scout projects, we keep
the medians looking good.
we hope the board of
supervisors will approve the
new guidelines in our rfp
process soon for the community
challenge grants so that we and
many others MAY apply again.
another partner organization
I want to thank is st aidan's
episcopal church that has
provided support and free space
for meetings and parties for
years for all the groups
described above.
I thank my spouse john
wilke, my daughter erin wilke
at they have both supported me
and all my endeavors.
Much gratitude to you PRESIDENT
Mandell and to all the members
of the board of supervisors for
commending the volunteer
service of so many residents of
our city.
thank you very much.
Thank you, betsy.
And I would just note that
betsy had to use her time to
advocate for more items on the
diamond heights community
association priority list.
Just please disturb.
it's just to give her thank
you.
thank you.
all right.
I think that concludes our 230
special order.
And MADAM Clerk, can you please
take us to our first 3 P.M.
Special order?
yes, the first 3:00 special
order is item 19 on today's
agenda.
It's a hearing of the board of
supervisors sitting as a
committee of the whole to hear
and receive updates on the
progress and implementation
status of the united states
department of justice
recommendations regarding
reforms within the police
department.
supervisor walton thank you
PRESIDENT MADAM and I would
like to continue this item to
our MAY 6th, 2025 what a
supervisors meeting.
The police department had a lot
of presentations and schedule
conflicts today and so that
works best for all of us.
great.
Supervisor walton I'm intrigued
that as a motion is there a
second seconded by melgar
before we take that before we
vote on that motion we need to
take public comments.
MADAM Clerk, please call for
public comment on the
continuance.
yes.
If you're here to speak on item
19 and its continuance to MAY
6th, 2025 please step forward
now.
this is not general public
comment.
it's just the continuance of
the item and a recommendation.
what is it regarding law
enforcement practices law
enforcement?
Yes.
Okay.
So you get to do a better job.
yes.
You are in big trouble.
I don't care.
I just tip I'm sorry.
Yes.
I don't have anything to say.
Covid 19 a certificate of
vaccination id.
Thank you for your comments.
See no other speakers, MR.
PRESIDENT.
all right.
Public comment on the
continuance is close.
Colleagues, we have a motion to
continue this hearing to MAY
six, 2025.
Board of supervisors meeting.
it's been seconded.
I'd like to say that without
objection.
Without objection this hearing
is contingent to MAY 6th, 2025
.
MADAM Clerk, let's go to our
next special order please call
items 20 through 23 together.
yes, items 20 through 23
comprise the hearing and
associated motions related to
the appeal of determination of
exemption from environmental
review under section for the
proposed project at 2142 to 20
second street which proposes to
demolish an existing single
family dwelling unit to
construct a new six to
construct a new six storey
building with five new units.
An item 21 affirms a sequel
determination.
Item 22 conditionally referred
reverses a single determination
in item 23 directs the clerk to
prepare findings to reverse a
determination.
supervisor walton.
Thank you so much PRESIDENT
Randleman and I would like to
make a motion to continue this
item to the tuesday, APRIL
15th, 2025 board of supervisors
meeting.
thank you.
Is there a second second and by
chen and we have to take public
comments on that.
MADAM Clerk please call for
public comment.
if you would like to speak
on items 23 through 23 and its
continuance, please step
forward.
You will have two minutes.
whatever the street we don't
care.
I mean this is all city
environment.
You understand the concept and
vironment.
so if we are attacked from
the skies and food poisoning
how do you take care of your
own vironment is explain
because you don't think it's
rude.
Yes, that's what I think you
are your standard now you don't
think it's environment.
okay.
you be dead soon.
I told you already.
We are under attack big time by
a fed.
you don't know it's coming.
It's all over the states you
already know 12 states attacked
last week.
In fact.
Tornadoes, fake wildfires.
Hello.
it's still wintertime.
I mean just spring, you know,
whatever environments.
Yes, of course you bet.
besides seeing no other
speakers come forward, MR.
PRESIDENT.
All right.
thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Public comment on the
continuance is closed this and
here we have a motion to
continue this hearing to the
APRIL 15th, 2025 board of
supervisors meeting.
I would like to take that
without objection if we can and
it looks like we can.
So without objection this
hearing and associated motions
are continued to APRIL 15th,
2025 and then MADAM Clerk, I
think we need to go back to
item 15.
yes, item number 15 is a
motion appointing chester
williams gabriella castelo enos
rumbough francis.
Abigail cabrera.
Jamie schmidt, shoon and laura
urban.
Terms ending DECEMBER 31st 2026
to the sugary drinks
distributor tax advisory
committee.
all right.
And I think can we take that
same house same call, MADAM
Clerk yes.
So yeah.
All right.
So we will take this item same
house, same call without
objection this motion is
approved.
Then MADAM Clerk, can you
please call item 16?
Item number 16 is a motion
appointing nicholas broussard
off term ended MARCH 17th, 2027
to the veterans affairs
commission and we can take this
item same house, same call.
Without objection this motion
is approved.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 17?
item number 17 is a motion
approving the mayor's
nomination for the appointment
of alphonso felder to the
municipal transportation agency
board of directors term ending
MARCH 1st, 2027 and we'll take
this item same house, same
call.
without objection the motion
is approved.
MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item 18?
Item number 18 is a motion
approving the mayor's
nomination for the appointment
of mattie scott to the police
commission for a term ending
APRIL 30th, 2026 and we will
take this item same house, same
call.
Without objection this motion
is approved.
And then MADAM Clerk, I think
we're going to go to our
committee reports.
please call item 24 yes
items 24 through 26 were
considered by the land use and
transportation committee at a
regular meeting on monday MARCH
17th, 2025 and were recommended
to the full board.
item number 24 it was impact
recommended as amended with a
new title.
It is an ordinance amending the
planning code to limit
restrictions on replacement
materials and window
replacement projects in certain
buildings and making
appropriate findings.
All right.
I think we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading MADAM
Clerk, can you please call item
20 five?
Item number 25 is an ordinance
amending the planning code to
allow tourist hotels and motels
to be used for interim housing
without abandoning or
discontinuing the hotel use
classification amending the
building code to allow interim
housing without thereby
changing without changing the
underlying occupancy
classification of the property
and amending appended p to
remove restriction that the
housing the emergency housing
be located on land owned or
leased by the city and making
appropriate findings and we can
take this item same house same
call without objection the
ordinance is passed on first
reading.
And MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item two six?
item number 26 is an
ordinance amending the planning
code to authorize a continuance
of nonconforming public parking
lots in the central summer
mixed use office and mixed use
residential districts through
DECEMBER 31st 2026 enabling an
existing parking lot operator
to apply for a conditional use
authorization for a five year
extension and making
appropriate findings.
And we'll take this item same
house, same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading.
and MADAM Clerk, let's go to
roll call first up on roll call
for introductions today is
supervisor supervisor
slaughter.
thank you, MADAM Clerk and
PRESIDENT Menem and colleagues
today I am introducing a
resolution to support sb 417 by
senator christopher her call to
ban and ab 736 by
assemblymember buffy wicks.
Collectively these bills are
known as the affordable housing
bond act of 2026 and these
bills were recently introduced
in the state legislature to
authorize a $10 billion general
obligation affordable housing
bond measure to be placed on
the JUNE 2026 ballot.
This bond would fund the
construction, rehabilitation
and preservation of tens of
thousands of affordable housing
units across the state.
This resolution follows a
letter recently submitted by
mayor lori to state to the
state in support of this
legislation.
If passed by the voters next
year this bond would fund the
construction of 35,000 new
homes affordable to very low
income, extremely low income
and homeless families across
california for at least 55
years.
It will also preserve and
rehabilitate 42,000 existing
affordable units in the face of
the extreme housing crisis.
Our city and state is facing.
This would make a significant
difference in helping san
francisco meet its affordable
housing need.
As a city we need to build
82,069 units by the year 2031
to meet to meet our arena
target and we are working to
zone to create that capacity.
But this bond is another
important piece of the puzzle
to provide the funding sources
.
additionally, 13 thousand
california families will
receive assistance to become
home homeowners as a result of
this bond and this legislation
protects and prioritizes some
of our state's most vulnerable
populations with set asides for
farmworker and tribal housing
affordable housing projects
in san francisco have directly
benefited from the programs
that would be funded by this
bond.
Most recently 4200 geary street
a 98 unit 100% affordable
apartment building for low
income seniors in the richmond
received a significant award
from the multiple family
housing program in 2021.
as of today america has more
than 10,000 affordable units
in the development pipeline and
many of these projects would
most likely benefit from this
bond.
This bond measure is the kind
of fiscally responsible
investment in affordable
housing that we should be
encouraging.
It will have no impact on the
2025 2026 state budget as the
bonds would not be issued until
2027 at the earliest and every
$1 spent by the state would be
matched by $4 in federal tax
credits, local grants and rent
payments.
Without this bond california
would leave billions of dollars
in federal tax credits on the
table.
I want to thank assembly member
wicks and senator codman for
introducing this important
legislation that will help
families achieve the dream of
affordable homeownership in san
francisco in all of california.
This legislation has strong
support in the legislature and
has been coauthored by senator
wiener and assembly member
haney.
I hope the governor and the
rest of the legislature will
recognize how critical this
bond measure will be for cities
like ours and will move forward
move us forward to the 2026
ballot.
I want to thank my colleagues
supervisors chen chan, dorsey
melgar, mahmud, sherril fielder
and guardian walton for
co-sponsoring this resolution
and working to create more
affordable housing
opportunities across our city
and the rest I submit.
thank you.
Supervisor sartor supervisor of
sherril.
colleagues I'm thrilled
today to join mayor lori
in introducing legislation that
doubles down on our investment
in the first year free program.
earlier this month the
budget and finance committee
held a hearing on first year
free during which we heard
success stories from businesses
who said that fee waivers saved
their dream of opening a new
storefront and gave them a key
leg up in the early days of
being open.
these stories are just some
of the almost 10,000
enrollments in the first year
free program in its first four
years.
But in many ways extending the
first year free program,
doubling down on the first year
free program is not about the
businesses and the successes
that we have seen so far.
it's about telling the
entrepreneurs who are thinking
about opening a new business
that san francisco is open for
business, that san francisco
wants them to be here to
unleash their own creativity
and build the vibrancy of this
city.
This city is recovering but now
is the time to commit further
and to spur this recovery even
higher.
And it's not just about waiving
fees.
it's again about being a
partner, not an obstacle but a
partner for the people.
And it is these people, these
entrepreneurs and the
immigrants who drive our
communities and who are going
to drive san francisco's
recovery.
We are only as strong.
Our economy is only as strong
as the small businesses that
power it.
And so when we make it easier
to start stay and grow a
business here, we're investing
in the future of our
neighborhoods, of our workforce
and our city as a whole.
Now while I would personally
prefer to extend this for more
than just a year because of the
ability of the city to take
advantage of some efficiencies
,I also want to commend the
budget committee for working so
hard to keep our city solvent
and especially budget committee
chair supervisor connie chan
whose commitment to fiscal
responsibility has been great
and a clear guide to me as
well.
And I want to thank you for
that support.
I want to thank mayor lori for
building on what we heard
in the hearing and for making
first your freeze extension one
of the first key pieces of the
permit S.F. Initiative.
And I also want to thank the
office of small business led by
katie tang and the treasurer
and tax collectors office.
And we saw amanda con freed
here earlier who carried the
implementation of this program
forward.
So let's keep pushing forward.
Let's keep breaking down
barriers and keep making san
francisco the best place to
open and run small business for
assessment.
thank you.
Supervisor sheryl supervisor
walton.
submitted thank you.
Supervisor chan.
thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I am asking us
to adjourn our meeting in honor
of former assistant chief of
the fire department art kenny.
Assistant chief kenny retire
from the fire department
in 2016 after serving 54 years
and rising to the rank of
assistant chief.
A career civil servant prior to
the fire department.
Assistant chief kenny serve
in the police department in the
san francisco police department
and for our recreation and
parks department.
He was a definition of
leadership.
He was a labor leader and even
as an assistant chief he came
out to many events to support
firefighters, social events,
campaign events all in support
of local 798.
Assistant chief kenny MAY
impact on his fellow
firefighters leading by example
and shaping so many who serve
with him.
His work ethics and dedication
to san francisco were second to
none and his presence is
greatly missed.
He was a dear and dedicated man
to his family.
His friends and to his
department to our fire
department and our city day
entire community is saddened by
his loss.
Our loss.
Thank you, chief kenny for your
service and I extend my deepest
sympathies and condolences to
his family and friends and our
fire department at this time.
For the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Thank you, supervisor chan.
Supervisor chen.
Thank you.
Supervisor dorsey.
Supervisor and engardio.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I am
introducing a resolution
calling on governor newsom and
the state legislature to
account $2 billion in flexible
funding over the next two years
to support public transit
agencies including the san
francisco municipal
transportation agency.
As fun to watch faces a looming
$320 million budget shortfall.
We need to send a clear message
and treat this moment like the
emergency it is by calling on
the governor and our state
legislature to step up and
support our transit agencies.
because without significant
public transportation funding
from the state, our
transportation system's up and
down the state risk a death
spiral of service cuts and
diminishing ridership during a
climate emergency and certainly
during an affordability
emergency.
We have lots of work to do
beyond the $2 billion from the
state.
we also need the massive mta
to use their own budget reserve
to ensure no immediate cuts or
lines are eliminated and to
explore our own general fund if
needed.
we also need to pass a
regional transportation bond
and explore all options to fund
transit locally including the
mayor's announcement of a
ballot fundraising committee
and other ballot measures like
a new prop l or a new tax
altogether.
it is time we tax
corporations and the wealthiest
to fund public transit.
To truly prioritize equity the
environment and supporting san
francisco's economic recovery.
The governor and state
legislature should not only
ensure that our local transit
agencies have enough funding to
prevent service cuts but enough
funding to support increased
service to draw riders back to
public transit.
I want to thank mayor lurie for
submitting a letter calling for
$2 billion in funding from the
state and the 70 for their
input and resources and support
for this resolution as well as
their ongoing state advocacy.
I also want to thank my initial
co-sponsors supervisor melgar
chan mahmood chan, sadr, dorsey
and walton.
Thank you.
The rest of thank you
supervisor fielder supervisor
mahmood.
colleagues today I requested
a budget and legislative
analyst's report for a
comparative post entitlement
permitting analysis asking to
analyze at least five other
major cities other cities
in the bay area and across
california are building faster
than us with the same interest
rates, the same labor
conditions and the same costs.
and yet san francisco remains
the slowest city to build
in the entire state in large
part due to a complicated and
inefficient permitting process.
san francisco currently has
thousands of entitled housing
units and yet there have been
yet to built delaying much
needed housing for our
residents.
while leaders in our city
have focused on improving the
entitlement process, this
report will examine what
happens after entitlement to
identify barriers and solutions
for delivering housing more
efficiently.
with over 1000 pages of
building code and multiple
agencies involved, small
businesses, homeowners and
housing developers face
unnecessary delays and high
costs.
this report will provide a
data driven approach to
reforming our permitting
system, helping us move beyond
piecemeal legislative fixes
towards comprehensive effective
solutions to shape the future
of our city's housing policy.
this study complements mayor
lurie and the planning
department's permit S.F.
Initiative to reform permitting
across key city agencies as
well as the planning
department's ongoing efforts to
update zoning and ensure new
housing can actually get built.
By learning from cities that
have successfully reduced
permitting delays, we can
create a more transparent and
functional system that supports
san francisco's economic
recovery.
i look forward to working with
the budget and legislative
analyst's team planning
department and permit team to
implement real change.
the rest I submit.
Thank you supervisor mahmood
PRESIDENT And thank you MADAM
Clerk.
Today I'm introducing a
resolution in support of senate
bill 222 principally authored
by state senator scott wiener
also known as the affordable
insurance and climate recovery
act.
The bill will hold oil
companies responsible for their
role in our worsening climate
and insurance crises.
Every year our planet goes
through more frequent and more
devastating climate disasters.
In 2024 we endured a series of
atmospheric rivers that flooded
san francisco and damaged or
destroyed numerous homes and
trees.
The damages from those storms
totaled $4.5 billion just just
a few months ago.
San francisco.
San francisco deployed our own
firefighters to help battle the
los angeles wildfires which
burned 58.4. Five square miles
of land, destroyed 16,200
structures displayed tens of
thousands of families and
caused $250 billion in damage.
these climate disasters have
prompted insurance providers to
exponentially raise their rates
with some rates going up by as
much as 48% in 2024.
Beyond that, providers have
declined to renew more than 2.8
million homeowner policies
in california between 2020 and
2022, including 531,000 homes
in los angeles county, many of
which were destroyed by the
palisades fire.
With nowhere to go,
policyholders must resort to
using the state's fair plan the
final option available for fire
insurance or even the fair
plan, however, has had to
significantly raise the cost of
coverage for policy holders as
the costs of climate disasters
have increased.
It is simply unfair and
inexcusable for policyholders
to be forced to pay the price
for a climate crisis that has
mostly been caused by oil
companies.
sb 222 will create a private
right of action so that those
injured by climate disasters
will be able to recover their
losses from the oil and gas
companies that misled the
public for decades about their
contribution to the climate
crisis.
the bill will also create a
direct cause of action for
insurers against these same
companies and allow the
insurers to recover for harms
to their businesses that result
from climate related impacts an
increase in costs through the
volatility of the insurance
market.
finally and certain
circumstances this bill will
require the fair plan to
exercise its right of
subrogation against oil and gas
companies to recover claims
paid toward large climate
driven events such as wildfires
.
I want to thank senator wiener
for authoring this legislation
and I also want to thank conor
johnston with the extreme
weather survivors for bringing
the legislation to our
attention and working with us
on the resolution.
And I want to thank calvin
in my office for his work on
this and the rest I submit.
thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar thank you
MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I am
introducing a hearing request
on the staffing and policies
for the san francisco police
department special victims unit
the special victims unit as for
you is tasked with critical
cases like sexual assault,
domestic violence, human
trafficking, elder abuse cases
that require multi-agency
coordination and increase
emotional and social
sensitivity.
There has been a 65.7%
reduction in staffing of the
special victims unit.
Four years ago there were 70
investigators assigned.
today we only have 24.
We are interested in learning
about the staffing for this
unit which deals with severe
and potentially fatal cases
in how it is impacted by spd's
overall staffing shortage and
as well as the continuity of
staffing meaning officers being
deployed to other activities.
Moreover, we want to discuss
how we as a city can
collaboratively develop short
term and long term strategies
to to address these impacts.
this is women's history
month and sadly as shown in the
latest family violence council
report sexual assault, domestic
violence and elder abuse still
disproportionately affect women
.
We want to better understand
the workflows and policies
guiding this work and how we
can support prioritizing these
cases so that investigations
are able to progress especially
as we are centering victims
in our approach to handling
cases of abuse.
as such we are requesting
the newly formed office of
victim and witness rights and
the sexual harassment and
assault response and prevention
to respond to report along with
the san francisco police
department.
Thank you to supervisor chen
walton and regard you for your
early co-sponsorship of this
hearing.
Also I have an in memoriam,
MADAM Clerk, for my dear
neighbor in ingleside terrace,
professor dewey wyllie and JR.
born in tupelo, mississippi
on NOVEMBER 10th of 1935, dewey
grew up in a family that valued
education, music and
resilience.
He got his love of learning
from his mom, a schoolteacher
in his love of music from his
dad, a talented musician and
band director.
From a young age, dewey had a
strong affinity for music.
He started playing the horn
when he was in second grade and
by the time he was in sixth
grade he became the best horn
player in his high school band.
After high school he majored
in voice at the university of
alabama where he excelled,
earning his degree and three
years.
dewey's musical pursuits
were put on hold for a short
time when he served in the
military stationed in germany
as an assistant to the lead
chaplain.
But after his service do we
return to his hometown to teach
music in his old middle school?
milam junior high.
In the mid 1960s, dewey dewey
joined the faculty of the san
francisco state university
school of music where he taught
voice for almost 30 years.
Do we was known for his
beautiful baritone voice.
His warmth is his incredible
height.
He was six foot four.
Dewey was loved inside and
outside the classroom at san
francisco state.
He moved to ingleside terraces
in 1967 where he was known for
decades for his daily walks
always with a cheerful greeting
for a neighbor and a passer by.
Dewey was a dedicated father
and loved his family deeply and
always had a smile.
Even though times were tough,
he kept his resilient positive
spirit even in the last months
of his life.
Professor dewey camp was a
cherished member of our
community who shared his
passion and love for music with
everyone around him.
He will be deeply missed.
There is a memorial service
this saturday at san francisco
state university.
If anyone is interested
in attending thank you so much.
And the rest I submit.
Thank you supervisor melgar.
MR. PRESIDENT.
that concludes the roll call
for introductions.
great.
let's go to public comment.
At this time the board welcomes
general public comment.
As you are lining up on your
right hand side of the chamber
along the curtains.
As stated earlier, we will
first hear remote general
public comment from an
individual vetted pursuant to
the americans with the
disability act.
MR. Kevin lamb is monitoring
the line.
Will you please bring the first
caller forward?
hello.
please confirm that you can
hear me and I will start.
we can hear you.
Hello.
This is michael petrelli
calling and I'm calling on
behalf of the traumatized
community in the castro over
the death of a homeless man
named dale.
We have not seen any action
from our elected officials
about a town hall to discuss
how to help our unhoused
neighbors in the castro so that
they don't die on the sidewalk
.
also we are traumatized by
the recent bashing of a man
named tony on MARCH 9th
in front of the castro theater.
he has launched a go fund me
page to pay for his medical
expenses.
unfortunately our elected
official in the castro is not
listening to the demands many
demands from traumatized people
that we want a town hall for
him to organize so that we can
tell him why we are angry about
this attack on tony that left
gay blood.
yes, gay blood was left on
the sidewalk in front of the
castro theater for two days.
that is unacceptable.
We as a traumatized community
really demand our elected
official start holding regular
town hall meetings.
The only people who are afraid
of town hall meetings are
republicans.
We see this across the country
that the gop does not want to
hear from angry constituents
and unfortunately that is the
situation in the castro with
our elected officials.
I must conclude by saying
that harvey harvey milk equals
healing.
Harvey would have called the
town hall meeting by now and I
hope our officials will soon
announce the town hall meeting
about this trauma.
thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
All right.
We'll go to the first
in-person.
go ahead.
so I'm not going to babysit
you for much longer.
I'm going to take a long break.
no, I'm sorry.
I need to go for a break.
Inspect us.
they are doing it alive.
So three months no women are
being used because woman you
see you young.
Easy to be older.
you know there be others.
So you are being used.
So I know that no climate
change here.
What is this you said?
No, no, no.
Yeah.
the attacks are real with
weapons.
You understand weapons of.
From technology here we are
under attack.
No climate change.
I mean there is climate change
but it's not what you are
talking about.
so no go.
Yeah.
okay.
We have to reopen the great I
want it to be reopened.
There are going to be a rally
this coming tuesday.
you are all welcome to join.
Bring your dogs.
It's going to be like part of
the revolution as well.
Protest reopened the great
highway.
okay.
I told you once that matter
feeds on space that feeds on
light produced by matter that
feeds on evolution, that feeds
on matter.
If you break any part of the
cycle, you're dead.
That's exactly what's going on
with humanity consciousness.
It is unnecessary tool.
When we achieve a status of
having no play battery above
us.
So if we don't have
consciousness we solve this
problem because no matter what
we need to evolve and it's
done.
we become both.
that's a now big mistake for
human beings.
They think they are the super
hot potato.
No.
Sorry guys.
You know what?
Eternity is above you.
that's absolute nonsense.
Which means that eternity is
the super, that's all.
If we don't play by these rules
which I explained what about
your then?
there you go.
I have a good night.
Thank you for your comments.
next speaker.
good afternoon, board of
supervisors.
For the record, my name's chris
ward klein.
I also go by sergeant klein of
the united states marine corps
active duty.
And I'm the ceo of a nonprofit
called haven.
Prejudice and violence ends.
Now all of you should have
received the fbi report today
sent to each of each one of
you.
It's very concerning and it's
accurate.
About two years ago I reached
out to the marine corps, the
department of defense and said
something is not right about
san francisco.
We were in the middle of covid
and things were not going abc
and it was just a little bit
screwed up.
People would write their
supervisors, they would write
the police department and then
weird things would happen to
them.
They would be in an accident
something would happen to their
kids.
That's because they were
putting they were being placed
on surveillance by the city
attorney's office.
So in this report it's named it
names dennis herrera and david
chiu.
and right now right before this
meeting I asked them to call
the department of defense, dhs
and the doj.
They have to have a serious
conversation.
They are culpable.
They are very culpable.
It's very concerning that you
get advice from the city
attorney's office and they only
give you the options through
technology of a, b and c
because they already have the
answers that they want you to
decide not a, b, c and d.
They only give you the three of
their options not the correct
option.
that will change.
It's being investigated.
Please read the report.
I'm not going to read it here
because it's very sensitive but
please read it.
it's very concerning.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
next speaker well, I did a
political speech last time I
was here.
now I'm going to talk about
religion.
I'm really tempted to do
politics because laura loomer
found out about this judge,
this communist judge that says,
you know, we have to turn the
plane around, bring all the
illegal aliens back.
And how his daughter is
connected with well, I don't
want to I've only got a minute
and a half.
Well, okay.
I discovered something
in regards to the return of
jesus christ that is quite
interesting.
I discovered that in 1995 we
had the 494th sabbath year take
place.
and I can prove this from
the year that jesus was
baptized.
I can actually prove that it
was the 490th sabbath year
started on APRIL fools.
It ended on MARCH 20th of 1996
and that indeed was the 498th
sabbath year from when joshua
crossed the jordan.
This is important because
in daniel chapter nine there
was a prophecy that said jesus
would come in 490 years.
And it's really amazing that
when joshua crossed the jordan
river there were precisely 600
blue nations of the moon before
the first jubilee.
A jubilee is every 49 years.
And the first time we have a
coming together with a complete
amount of days with years is
after 1447 days.
And that corresponds with 49
new moons, 49 lunar months.
In other words, within 90s.
So it's like GOD is telling us
the jubilee year is very
important.
That 498th year okay in the
middle of that 480th year that
we call 1995 and a smidgen of
1996 began the 70th jubilee.
It also ended the times of the
gentiles which was 2520 years
from solomon's temple being
destroyed.
this is incorrect.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker please.
hello.
San francisco county board of
supervisors.
My name is julie three.
I'm appearing before you today
to appeal to your sense of duty
to protect the members of your
community from the covid 19
vaccine and support any
victim's injured me myself and
I being one of them.
after my two shots
in medicine I suffered micro ag
apathy two detached retinas and
I'm suffering from a heart
condition.
I'm from butte county and I
travel down here today to with
another whistleblower one who
left owens junior to alert as
many counties as possible.
I have spent the past three
years since being forced to
resign my health care job
rather than take the deadly
booster.
To speak out and warn people.
My request is for you to have
an official agenda item or a
hearing set as soon as possible
to hear directly from medical
freedom doctors and researchers
who will describe how this
vaccine is harmful to every
human being.
It should never be injected
into pregnant women or healthy
children.
Take down all references to
this product being safe and
effective from your website.
I'm a former health care worker
as I said in chico.
I am also a retired h r
executive of 25 years
in silicon valley and now I'm
lead investigator for verizon
where aecom, an organization
that helps wixom victims file
their vaccine adverse event
reports and I produced data for
the public.
I will work with your health
commission to train them on how
to access report adverse data
as of the end of FEBRUARY.
There are 96,682 injured people
from the covid shot
in california alone 7009 are
children 731 are deaths my
mother being one of them a 79
year resident of sunnyvale,
california.
Five are dead children, please
I'm begging you to take this
seriously.
I'm going to hand you some
information here.
I've got 13 doctors listed at
the end of my credentials that
will come in again speak to
your health commissioners.
I know your I know that you're
dedicated to public health but
there's got to be some you've
got to be taken seriously.
thank you so much.
thank you for your comments.
Someone will come up if you
have to pick up those papers.
next speaker please.
On APRIL 14th, 2022 department
of health and human services
secretary harvey episode said
this regarding the covid 19
vaccines quote we know these
vaccines are killing people of
color black, latino, indigenous
people at about two times the
rate of white americans.
My name is ronald f owens JR.
I was a public information
officer at the california
department of public health for
more than 14 years.
I brought this information
to my management multiple
locations but unfortunately
they made it about me not about
you, not about the 40 million
other californians as they
muzzled me.
but I will not and did not
muzzle myself.
So on DECEMBER 31st I retired
prematurely.
I immediately incurred a 55%
pay cut.
the difference between my
salary and my pension is not
about money.
It's about doing the right
thing.
last JULY I sent this board
and 57 other county board of
supervisors all this
information.
I followed up in DECEMBER.
I sent this board and the 57
other boards of supervisors
last
people filed entries in the
vaccine adverse event reporting
system.
two people died.
You have a duty to stop
promoting, stop administering
and stop distribute ing the
covid 19 vaccines because they
are killing people.
thank you for your
comments.
next speaker.
good afternoon.
Many of you are familiar faces
to me.
my name is ellen lee jo.
I run for san francisco mayor
in 2020 for 2019 and 2018.
I am as conservative mother, a
christian and I am opposed.
The vaccine that you have lied
especially not the new people.
the old perez border
supervisor.
I have been sending many of the
warning to you.
It is a bioweapon.
The covid 19 is a bioweapon by
the deep state agenda to try to
take down america and I echo
with my brother in here and my
sister in here.
I was a public health worker
for san francisco for more than
15 years.
many of you know me because I
ran the campaign.
I walk with you in your life
and you chose the evil life.
I am here today to urge you
to end all website vaccination
injection for encouragement
that you bribery you buy people
to vaccine, you give them
incentive for testing out and
all those are illegal.
it's crime against humanity
.
I also urge you to save san
francisco and make it safe.
Make it clean.
make it in america.
Stop using our public money to
murder our very own children.
The fancy name for abortion
stop using our money and
support the drug dealers and
keep them 5 million drug
needles a year.
and so call supporting the
drug dealers.
If you are not ashamed I am
ashamed.
I am ashamed.
Working for the for almost 20
years and knowing a bunch of
murders criminals running our
city hall by inactivate by the
actblue super pact.
None of you will be elected
into the office you are pri and
pay and bought into the office.
And you all know it's true.
and yes I am not ashamed
supporting my PRESIDENT.
thank you for your comments.
Next speaker please.
good afternoon supervisors.
My name is richard steve
peterson and you've heard me
speak before before I was on a
seven year project to build a
house on an empty lot and that
was my retirement.
So I decided to switch
retirement and perhaps looking
over the ordinance of your last
board of supervisors PRESIDENT
Aaron peskin for fortune
telling that seems simple
enough the law says and the
ordinance excuse me says that
after you submit your
application for fortune telling
15 later 15 days later the
permit should be granted or
not.
I've waited two months and it
hasn't been granted.
I'd paid money to the city.
It hasn't been granted.
So to add to my last week where
I was waving around my 1090
nines the pink copies I want to
complain about the red tape
in san francisco.
It really is impossible to do
anything in this city even
change professions.
I graduated from hastings as a
and became a patent attorney
and spent 50 years in this city
and northern california
practicing law that's
intellectual property is kind
of like fortune telling.
Well I'm retired now and I need
another profession so what more
a logical profession than
fortune telling that is up to
the police department to issue.
thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker someone's coming.
MADAM Clerk, if you could to
the supervisor and I have one
for adam.
okay.
I am gladys wong, a senior
resident owner of 47 lucky
in district nine I am being
honest, straightforward
requesting your assistance to
remove off parking on lucky
street between 24th and 25th.
previously the former mayor and
vf9 overruled san francisco
fire department to deny us that
removal will make the streets
safer for lucky street
residents.
allowing fire trucks and
ambulance uninterrupted access
to the buildings on lucky
street it will provide it will
provide sidewalk clearance on
lucky for pedestrians and
handicap access since the
parking requires vehicles to
park on the sidewalks, it will
allow homeowners and renters
who have garages and driveways
adequate access to garages and
driveways which are many times
hard to access due to parked
cars.
It will discourage illegal
activities such as drug use,
public urination, defecation,
trash dumpling and graffiti.
It will create consistency with
no parking provision on lucky
street between 25th and 26 and
with neighboring alleys barmy
horace virgil cypress lilac
osage and orange is that.
please review the folders
I've prepared for better
understanding any feedback
would be appreciated.
thank you.
Thank you so much for your
comments.
next speaker hello.
I have heard that this board
MAY intend to make recovery
first the primary objective of
the city's drug policy
absconding compassion and
science.
of course this will mostly
affect poor people who suffer
from addiction not the wealthy.
Now you seem to be able to do
whatever the they want without
recourse.
I have to wonder why aren't
abuses by the powerful and
wealthy considered disorders?
for example we have
substance use disorder but what
about weird control disorder
where our tax dollars spent are
spent disproportionately on
murdering black and brown
children worldwide especially
in palestine and congo right
now?
but let's be clear white
children asian children,
indigenous children every child
in this country is suffering
due to our tax dollars being
misspent on white supremacy.
Yes, white kids are hurt and
stunted by white supremacy too.
Or how about when a ceo goes on
the news to say that they want
120 hour work week from their
employees or that when wealthy
the wealthy elite who say that
vaccines are a hoax so poor
people only get sicker making
them even more vulnerable and
controllable.
Or the billionaires who want to
control our genders and bodies
and uteruses marrying off
little girls literal child
brides in america to trap them,
to rape them and force
childbearing on their little
bodies.
And since they're minors they
can't even initiate a divorce
until they're 18 or the church
that's still covering up their
child predator priests or the
police who can never seem to
save kids from mass school
shooters but conceive a white
supremacist after they've
murdered black and brown kids
and adults over and over again
or the health care overlord to
deny us care send us to our
graves in massive debt or the
oil corporations that lied to
us about climate change so that
they could kill our only
habitat for profit or the
plastics industry who has non
consensually infiltrated our
very cells, our very brains and
tissues and blood with
microplastics?
Where are the disorders for
these outrageous abuses?
Where is the accountability for
their crimes against us?
The public, the people?
And people are wondering how we
got here.
I know how because of you all
of you our, your collaboration
with the amoral wealthy elites
anything to make a profit
right?
also is anyone else
terrified by what they just
heard in this public comment?
is this a sign of times to
come?
thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hearing I'm here
concerning the resolution that
max carter oliver stone.
First I want to commend you all
for nominating mattie scott as
a as a police commissioner on
today.
Also but I am here because I
want to thank again matt darcy
for helping to implement this
resolution on other ways to pay
tipsters to come forth and to
keep them safe while doing so
and that they don't have to be
revealed.
And because back in the day the
accuser had to see his his
accuser.
And that's why people don't
come forth.
I have a $250,000 reward and no
one has come forth because
they're scared because they're
scared of retaliation.
They're scared of another
family being a member being
murdered.
so I understand that.
But this resolution will stop
that of people being scared.
So that's mothers like myself
can heal from our children
being murdered on the streets
of san francisco next month
will be my son's birthday APRIL
6th.
And still no resolution, no
nothing.
But I'm praying that this
resolution passes by the board
of supervisors.
and matt dorsey, I want to
thank you two for for taking
this on.
thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
Is there any other individuals
who would like to provide
public comment today?
good afternoon.
MR. CHAIRMAN, members of the
board of supervisors I am amos
brown, PRESIDENT Emeritus of
the san francisco branch of the
national association for the
advancement of colored people.
I also stand today as pastor
of the historic third baptist
church.
for now 49 years and will be
retiring come this JULY the
.
number one I read something
that shook me last night and I
read it to you.
world war two veteran
medgar evers whom PRESIDENT
Trump called a great american
hero has been erased from the
arlington national cemetery
website which featured a
section honoring black
americans who fought in the
nation's wars.
the U.S. Army purged the
section that had lauded the
late army sergeant and civil
rights leader who was
assassinated by a white
supremacist in jackson in 1963
.
the decision to erase evers
is named came after an
executive order by trump to
eliminate all diversity
equality and inclusion
programs.
End of quote all my friends as
a former member of this board I
beg you today to appeal to your
staff to craft a resolution
number one condemning this
attack on diversity and
inclusion.
And number two, calling on the
san francisco to with a
righteous indignation cry out
against the assault that's been
perpetrated.
Against my late mentor medgar
evers who brought me here
in 1956 after I had organized
the first youth council of the
national association for the
advancement of colored people
at the age of 14.
in the wake of that evil and
brutal killing lynching of one
emmett till and it took this
nation 106 years to even adopt
an anti-lynching bill.
that's what was done by the
biden harris administration.
Minute to minute or we raise
one worthy minutes to next time
we get to but I'm off.
I'm a former member of this
board.
you don't know it.
you know you cannot afford
illegal to manage a few
minutes.
the time is up.
So reverend brown, I'm going to
ask you to wrap up.
yes.
But this measure I'm appealing
to you to act on it.
all right.
We got your aaron brown to the
attorney's office.
thank you.
I had to write public comment
is now close.
but for yourself.
all right, MADAM Clerk,
let's go to our adoption
without hope.
We did that already?
No, we didn't.
Let's go to our adoption
committee reference a minute.
this issue is if you can
identify all right 31 point.
So the hurry.
all right.
We're going to recess for you.
Are you are we recessing or are
we continuing?
all right.
We're continuing, MADAM Clerk.
let's try it.
Let's go to our for adoption.
that committee referenced
agenda items 30 through 30 two
yes item 30 through 32 were
introduced for adoption without
committee reference.
A unanimous vote is therefore
required for adoption of the
resolution on first appearance
today.
Alternatively, a member MAY
require resolution on first
reading to go to committee.
all right.
I don't I do not see anybody
asking to sever any of these
items.
so MADAM Clerk, could you call
the roll on the on items 332
yes on items 30 through 32
supervisor sauder solder I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton supervisor
walton on the focker on the
floor adoption without
committee reference supervisor
chin I can I supervisor chen
chin chin I supervisor dorsey
dorsey I supervisor engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandolin mandolin I supervisor
melgar I melgar either lebanese
than we let's see we have all
of you without objection these
resolutions are adopted and
then MADAM Clerk do we have any
imperative agenda items?
we do not have any
imperative agenda items today.
Could you read the in memoriam?
Yes.
Today's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individuals
on behalf of supervisor chan
for the late art kenny and on
behalf of supervisor melgar for
the late professor dewey
william camp JR.
colleagues I believes that
that brings us to the end of
our agenda, MADAM Clerk is it
do we have any further business
before us today?
That concludes our business for
today.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.